A Guide to the William Couper Papers, 1901-1964
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
William Couper Papers, 1901-1964
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00053
The papers are filed in 36 manuscript boxes (13 cubic feet)and also contain oversized material located in map cases.
The papers consist largely of manuscripts (drafts, galleys, proofs), notes, and other research material relating to Couper's interest in the history of Lexington and Rockbridge County (Virginia), the Virginia Military Institute, and the Shenandoah Valley. Other topics include the construction of Fort Jackson, South Carolina in 1917, and General Stonewall Jackson.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the collection was donated by John Lee Couper in 1964.
Biographical/Historical Information
William Couper (shown here during World War I) spent the majority of his professional life devoted to the Virginia Military Institute and to the study of VMI, Lexington and Rockbridge County, and Virginia history. His terms as VMI's Business Executive and Historiographer encompassed thirty years, but before, during and subsequent to that period he served in many other official and unofficial capacities. He was a noted authority on local and regional history, and on the life and times of General Stonewall Jackson. At VMI, in addition to his official duties, he was responsible for the initial organization and preservation of the Institute's rich historical holdings, including it's unique collection of alumni biographical and genealogical materials.
William Couper Chronology.
Significant Events.
1884 Born November 16 at "Oakland" in Norfolk, Virginia.
1901 Graduated from the Norfolk Academy and entered the Third Class at the Virginia Military Institute.
1904 Graduated from VMI with distinction (Engineering course).
1906 Received a Bachelor of Science degree in Civil Engineering (railroad option) from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology.
1906 - 1917 Worked with the Pennsylvania Railroad at New York City on construction, operating and harbor work; he played a major role in the construction of the railroad tunnels and terminals for NYC.
1912 Published "History of the Engineering, Construction and Equipment of the Pennsylvania Railroad New York Tunnels and Terminals. "
1917 June Commissioned Major in the United States Army Quartermaster Corps and assigned as Construction Officer at Camp Jackson, Columbia, South Carolina.
1918 March Promoted to Lt. Col., in charge of the building of the camp that became Fort Jackson.
1920 Completed Army service in March; prepared on request a plan of development for the future of VMI, which was adopted by the VMI Board of Visitors in June.
1920 - 1921 Assistant General Manager of the Associated General Contractors of America
1921 - 1924 Employed jointly by the Texas Company and the Southern Acid and Sulphur Company as an engineer to develop sulphur properties in Brazoria Co., Texas.
1924 Appointed Business Executive in charge of the business activities at the Veterans's Bureau Station at Perry Point, Maryland, where a supply depot, hospital for neuropsychiatric patients, rehabilitation schools and automobile reconditioning shops were operated.
1925 Appointed Business Executive at the Virginia Military Institute.
1931 - 1933 Secretary and Treasurer of the VMI Alumni Association.
1933 Published The VMI New Market Cadets
1934 Appointed VMI Historiographer.
1934 - 1935 President of the Association of Military Colleges and Universities in the U. S.
1934 - 1945 Secretary and Treasurer of the Southern Conference (Athletics)
1936 Published Claudius Crozet
1939 Published One Hundred Years at VMI and The Register of Former Cadets
1946 -1948 Vice President and President of the Southern Conference.
1952 Published A History of the Shenandoah Valley
1954 Retired from his positions at VMI.
1964 Died February 15 at his home in Lexington, Virginia. Buried Norfolk, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The William Couper Papers document a portion of the life and career of a man notable for his research and publications about the history of the Virginia Military Institute; the Lexington, Rockbridge County and Shenandoah Valley (Virginia) areas; Virginia history and genealogy; Civil War General Stonewall Jackson; and Claudius Crozet.
A significant portion of the papers consist of publication manuscripts (drafts, galleys, proofs), notes, and other material related to Couper's major historical research projects (many of which were published). These include One Hundred Years at VMI, a four volume comprehensive history of the Institute from it's founding in 1839 through 1939; The VMI New Market Cadets, containing biographical information about the VMI students and staff who fought in the Civil War battle on May 15, 1864; Claudius Crozet, a biography of the notable 19th century Virginia Civil Engineer; History of the Shenandoah Valley; and "Stonewall Jackson Day by Day," a chronological account including events, anecdotes, clippings, transcribed correspondence, notes, and maps.
Couper's passion for the history of Lexington and Rockbridge County (VA) is evident in the substantial amount of local history research material found in his papers. Included are notes on a wide range of local history topics, as well as extensive research material (notes and maps) concerning the history of many local properties and the Lexington cemetery.
The papers also include material concerning the construction of Fort Jackson, South Carolina; Couper's speeches and addresses; maps; scrapbooks; photograph albums; and miscellaneous correspondence.
Organization
The papers are organized into 12 series.
1. Books and Articles by William Couper-- Research, drafts, related materials.
2. Stonewall Jackson Research Materials.
3. Lexington and Rockbridge County (Virginia) History.
4. Genealogy
5. Gen. William Harvie Richardson Subject File.
6. VMI Class of 1904.
7. Fort Jackson, South Carolina, construction.
8. Correspondence.
9. Speeches and Addresses.
10. Maps.
11. Photograph Albums.
12. Printed Material.
Additional Descriptive Data
Related Materials at VMI
Researchers should note that, because Couper served in several different positions at VMI, many of his professional papers are located in various record groups in the VMI Archives. These include records of the Business Office, Alumni Association, and various administrative subject files (e.g. Southern Conference).
Related Manuscript Collections in other Repositories
The Virginia Historical Society (Richmond, Virginia) holds additional William Couper and Couper Family papers.
Items on Loan
In 1974, at the request of the Fort Jackson (SC) Museum, selected Couper papers relating to the construction of Fort Jackson were placed on indefinite loan to the Museum.
Contents List
- Books and Articles by William Couper. Research, drafts, related materials
  - One Hundred Years at VMI 1935-1939 (Box 1 - 7)
    Materials relating to the research and publication of Couper's four volume history of the Virginia Military Institute, published in 1939. Related items are located in oversized.
    - Galley Proofs (Box-folder 1:1-2)
    - Page Proofs (Box-folder 1:3 - 2:1)
    - Manuscript (Box-folder 2:1 - 4:2)
    - Research notes related to manuscript (Box-folder 4:3 - 7:5)
    - Research notes: Miscellaneous VMI-related. (Box-folder 28:1-8;)
  - The VMI New Market Cadets 1930-1933 (Box 8 - 9)
    Notes, correspondence, and financial records related to the publication of Couper's book about the VMI cadets who fought at the Battle of New Market (Virginia) in May 1864. This book was published in 1933.
    - Notes - The VMI New Market Corps. (Box-folder 8:1)
    - Notes - correspondence of Cadet J. Beverly Stanard (Box-folder 8:2)
    - Reference file - Battle Accounts (Box-folder 8:3)
      Thom, Morton, Sturm.
    - Reference file - Notes on opposing commanders (Box-folder 8:4)
      Notes by Joseph Reid Anderson, Jr., Torbett and Echols, re: Gen. Breckinridge and Gen. Sigel.
    - Reference file - printed materials (Box-folder 8:5)
    - Correspondence 1933-1934 (Box-folder 8:6-8)
    - VMI New Market Cadets (Box-folder 8:9)
      Paperback copy of the final publication
    - Financial Records (Box-folder 8:10-11)
      Bank books, account book, balance sheets relating to the publication of the New Market book.
    - Speech May 15, 1939 (Box-folder 9:1)
      New Market anniversary address delivered in Stonewall Jackson Memorial Hall. Typescript draft.
    - New Market pamphlet 1942 (Box-folder 9:2-3)
      Correspondence re: publication of the pamphlet; printed copies with corrections by William Couper.
    - Reinterment of New Market Cadets; Headstones (Box-folder 9:4)
  - Claudius Crozet 1936 (Box-folder 9:5-7)
    Galley proofs, manuscript, notes
  - History of the Shenandoah Valley 1952 (Box 12-14)
    - Manuscript for publication (Box 12-13)
    - Research material (Box-folder 14:1-6)
      Materials related to the manuscript and publication, including notes, correspondence, and newspaper clippings.
  - Articles by or about William Couper (Box-folder 30:4-5; 32-5)
- Stonewall Jackson. Stonewall Jackson Day by Day, Research Material. (Box 10-11)
  Unpublished research material concerning the life of Thomas J. Jackson (General Stonewall Jackson).
  - Stonewall Jackson- chronological notes (Box 10)
    Detailed notes regarding Jackson's life, proceeding chronologically from birth to death.
    - Notes for period 1818-1853 (Box-folder 10:1)
    - Notes for period 1854-1860 (Box-folder 10:1A)
    - Notes for period 1861 Jan-1862 May 14 (Box-folder 10:2)
    - Notes for period 1862 May 15-Aug 26 (Box-folder 10:3)
    - Notes for period 1862 Aug 17-Nov 30 (Box-folder 10:4)
    - Notes for period 1862 Dec 1-1863 May 15 (Box-folder 10:5)
  - Stonewall Jackson- Subject files and supplementary materials
    - Subject index to supplement (Box-folder 11:1)
    - Addresses and articles about Jackson (Box-folder 11:2)
    - Abilities - Correspondence (Box-folder 11:3)
    - Estimates - Letters (Box-folder 11:4)
    - Maps - Poems (Box-folder 11:5)
    - Portraits - Sundays (Box-folder 11:6)
    - Miscellaneous notes (Box-folder 11:7)
    - Addresses by William Couper re: Jackson (Box-folder 11:8)
    - Correspondence (misc.) re: Jackson (Box-folder 11:9)
    - Jackson genealogical material (Box-folder 11:10; 36:00)
    - Map by Couper, Movements of Gen. T. J. Stonewall Jackson, 1861-1863(printed copies). (Box-folder 11:11; 36:00)
    - Photocopies- Jackson's report of the Battle of Port Republic. (Box-folder 11:12)
    - Clippings. (Box-folder 11:13)
- Lexington and Rockbridge County (Virginia) History
  One of Couper's primary research interests was the history of the Lexington and Rockbridge County area. This series, including notes, clippings, & other material, covers a wide range of local history topics. In addition to the files listed below, related material is located separately in oversized (map cases).
  For related series, see Maps.
  - Subject Files, Local History topics.
    - Misc. local history topics, articles, clippings (Box-folder 14:7)
    - VMI and Washington and Lee University (Box-folder 14:8)
    - Churches (Box-folder 14:9)
    - Troubadour Theater (Box-folder 14:10)
    - Post Office (Box-folder 15:1)
    - Prison Bounds (Box-folder 15:2)
    - Mills (Box-folder 15:3)
    - New Stonewall Jackson Hospital (Box-folder 15:4)
    - Rockbridge Historical Society - notes (Box-folder 15:5)
    - Rockbridge Historical Society - proceedings, 1939-1960. (Box-folder 15:6)
  - Property Files
    Research material concerning local properties, including notes on plats, deeds, lots, property owners.
    - Large Plats (Box-folder 15:7)
      Rockbridge, Augusta, Botetourt Counties
    - Notes-Lexington/RC Property (Box-folder 15:8)
      Concerning lots, deeds, grants, early lots and annexations, maps.
    - Notes-Lexington/RC Property (Box-folder 15:9)
      Concerning property owners, old places, development So. of Lexington.
    - Notes-Lexington R/C property, old deeds (Box-folder 15:10)
    - Notes-Lexington R/C property; maps on deeds, grants. (Box-folder 16:1)
    - Index of deeds in my notebooks; Notebooks #16-#21. (Box-folder 16:2)
    - Notes re: 106 White St; misc. notes. (Box-folder 16:3)
    - Notes re: Lexington zoning. (Box-folder 16:4)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #1 - #2. (Box-folder 16:5)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #3 - #6. (Box-folder 16:6)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #7 - #8. (Box-folder 17:1)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #9 - #10. (Box-folder 17:2)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #11 - #12. (Box-folder 17:3)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #13 - #14. (Box-folder 17:4)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #15 - #16. (Box-folder 18:1)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #17 - #18. (Box-folder 18:2)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #19 - #20. (Box-folder 18:3)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #21 - #22. (Box-folder 18:4)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #23 - #24. (Box-folder 19:1)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #25 - #26. (Box-folder 19:2)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #27 - #28. (Box-folder 19:3)
    - Notes from Rockbridge Co. Property Books #24 - #25. (Box-folder 19:4)
  - Lexington Cemetery (Stonewall Jackson Cemetery)
    - History of the Lexington Cemetery (Box-folder 20:1)
    - Index to Cemetery Notebooks (1962); alphabetical listing of names (Box-folder 20:2)
    - Cemetery Notebooks, #1-2 (Box-folder 20:3)
    - Cemetery Notebooks, #3-5 (Box-folder 20:4)
    - Notebook- grave locations (Box-folder 20:5)
    - Cemetery Maps (hand drawn by Couper). (Box-folder 20:6)
  - Local History- clippings and scrapbooks. 1890-1962 (Box 31-32; 34-35)
- Genealogy Notes
  - Lexington and Rockbridge County families. (Box-folder 21:1)
  - Virginia Families (Box-folder 21:2)
- William Harvie Richardson Subject File.
  General William Harvie Richardson had a long and close association with VMI. He served as the Adjutant General of Virginia and on the VMI Board of Visitors from 1841-1876. The transcriptions of correspondence are of letters found in the official correspondence of VMI Superintendent Francis H. Smith. The original letters are located in the VMI Archives, Records of the Superintendent.
  - Biographical information, correspondence about Richardson, misc. notes. (Box-folder 21:3)
  - Correspondence to VMI, 1863 - transcriptions (Box-folder 21:4)
  - Correspondence to VMI, 1864 - transcriptions (Box-folder 21:5)
  - Correspondence to VMI, 1865-1870 - transcriptions (Box-folder 21:6)
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box-folder 21:7)
- Virginia Military Institute Class of 1904
  Couper graduated from VMI in 1904, and maintained contact with his classmates throughout his life.
  - Correspondence regarding reunions 1909-1910; 1914; 1918-1919; 1924 (Box-folder 22:1)
  - Notes regarding the Class (Box-folder 22:2)
  - Form letters re: reunions (Box-folder 22:3)
  - Reunion book correspondence, 1925 (Box-folder 22:4)
  - Class book letters and reunion books. 1907-1924 (Box-folder 22:5)
  - Class reunion photograph. June 13, 1954 (Box-folder 22:6)
    The photograph includes the following individuals: Robert B. Allport, Samuel K. Funkhouser, Alfred P. Upshur, Thomas C. Gordon, William Couper, Paul R. Camp, James S. Easley, Ellis C. Caldwell.
- Fort Jackson, South Carolina, contruction. 1917-1923
  Fort Jackson was constructed in 1917 to meet Army training needs during World War I. Couper served as construction Quartermaster.
  - Ft. Jackson Suspension File, 1923 (Box-folder 23:1)
  - Reports. 1917-1918
    - Completion Report, Camp Jackson, Columbia SC. January 17, 1918 (Box-folder 23:2)
      Written by William Couper
    - Financial Report (Box-folder 23:3)
      Analyses of Costs. Original Cantonments. From start to Dec. 31, 1917. Camps Custer, Grant, Jackson, Lee, Sherman.
    - Consolidated Daily Report of Cars Handled. Jan-Oct 1917 (Box-folder 23:4)
    - U. S. Army Base Lighter Construction. 1918 (Box-folder 23:5-6)
    - Final Report on Lighter Construction
  - Ft. Jackson Printed Materials
    - Manual for Constructing Quartermasters (Box-folder 24:1-2; 4)
    - Specifications for the sale of thirteen Army camps. (Box-folder 24:3)
    - Organization and Operation of the Mobilization, Procurement, and Delivery System of the Construction Division of the Army (Box-folder 24:5)
    - Manual for Field Auditors (Box-folder 24:6)
    - Report of the Board of Review of Construction. 1920 (Box-folder 24:7)
    - The Work of the Construction Division of the Army. 1920 (Box-folder 24:8)
    - 50th Anniversary History, Ft. Jackson, SC, 1917-1967 (Box-folder 24:9)
- Correspondence.
  - Henry Peck Fry letters, Incoming. 1942-1945 (Box-folder 25:1-3)
    Fry (VMI Class of 1901) was a newspaperman and writer.
  - Miscellaneous correspondence. 1930-1960 (Box-folder 25:4)
- Speeches and Addresses. 1926-1956
  Index, notes and/or full-text of Couper's speeches.
  - Index to addresses (Box-folder 26:1)
    Typescript list of speeches, compiled by Couper.
  - Speeches- notes and/or text (Box-folder 27:2 - 28:4)
    Topics include: VMI history, Stonewall Jackson; Claudius Crozet; Battle of New Market; Rockbridge County maps; early Rockbridge County history; other local history topics (Lexington/Rockbridge Co. Virginia).
- Maps
  Many of the items in this series were hand drawn by William Couper and are annotated, and/or are accompanied by related correspondence and notes. Some additional maps are filed separately in oversized (map case).
  - Virginia Military Institute Maps (Box-folder 29:1-2; 36.)
    Includes notes, keys
  - Lexington (Virginia) Maps
    Many of these, particularly the plat maps, were drawn by William Couper.
    - Lexington- lots, street maps, Campbell Farm (Box-folder 29:3)
    - Lexington - printed (Box-folder 29:4)
    - Lexington street map (Box 36)
      City limits drawn in for 1778; 1847; 1850; 1877.
    - Lexington street map. 1912 (Box 36)
      Drawn by J. A. Champe, Jr. (1912); reprinted 1952.
    - Lexington street map, unmarked. 1958
    - Sketch from aerial map of Lexington (Box 36)
    - Lexington in the Benjamin Borden Grant. 1955 (Box 36)
      By D. E. Brady, with notations by William Couper.
    - Borden's Grant. September 1927 (Box 36)
      By D. E. Brady
    - Lexington, 1932 Charter. (Box 36)
    - Map showing Borden Grant Line (Box 36)
    - Plat map. John W. Fuller, David McKinley, William Taylor. (Box 36)
    - Plat Map. Land of John Hoffman, surveyed 9-2-1819. (Box 36)
    - Plat Map. HH-356. 8-18-1860. Sold to Sally C. P. Miller. Col Alto. Survey by Jas. C. C. Moore (1853). (Box 36)
    - Plat map, DB A-350. Isaac Campbell to George Brown. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, B-460. William Moore to John Hoffman. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, L-520. Elizabeth Hoffman and Daniel Hoffman to James McDowell. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, NN-367. E. S. Tutwiler's lots. Recorded 1-3-1874 (Box 36)
    - Plat map. The James Campbell Farm. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. The Campbell Farm, EE-229. (Box 36)
    - Plat of Town Lots Laid Off and Sold by William A. Rhodes, 5th Oct. 1867. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. DB 52-271. Survey made by James C. C. Moore in 1845. (McDowell St., Main, to Woods Creek, Jordan St. Sellers Ave.) (Box 36)
    - Plat map. 27 Lots on Plat of 1845 (Box 36)
    - Plat map. Division of Campbell Land, East Area between South Main-Taylor-Houston Sts. By D.E. Brady. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. W. A. Rhoads Development (Taylor St.) (Box 36)
    - Sketch of street map of Lexington from Insurance maps. (Box 36)
    - Plan for Defending Lexington when there was only four hours to do it in, from an attack of infantry.(3 copies- From National Archives). (Box 36)
    - Reconnaissance Map, U. S. Geological Survey, reproduced 1923. (Box 36)
  - Rockbridge County Maps
    - Map of Rockbridge County showing Highways, 1950. (Box 36)
    - Sketch map of Rockbridge County, unmarked. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, Richard Woods. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, C-232. Lapsleys to Zachariah Johnson. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, C-393. William Graham to Andrew Reid. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, DB-5-257. Borden to Craighead to John Bowyer. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. Sunnyside in 1858. Telford(Tedford). (Box 36)
    - Plat map, A-7. Joseph Walker to William Graham. (Box 36)
    - Plat map, DB 117-167. L. D. Hamric and Carolyn E. to T. B. Martin. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. Will Book 20-280. Unidentified. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. The Home Place. Ruff Estate. Will Book 20-280. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. 1-103. C. W. Barger Estate. Attached EE-228. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. DB 135-57. Surveyed for T. B. Martin. (1922). (Box 36)
    - Plat map. C-431. Dower of Elizabeth Moore. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. 1-104. Survey by D. E. Brady, 1953. (Box 36)
    - Plat map. DB 130-477. White Farm. (Box 36)
    - Plat of Area around Wilson Suphur Spring, compiled Dec. 1941 by D.E. Brady. (Box 36)
  - Virginia/West Virginia Misc. Maps
    - Virginia counties, showing county lines. (Box 36)
    - Jefferson Co., West Virginia. (Box 36)
    - Berkeley Co., West Virginia. (Box 36)
    - The Valley of Virginia. (Box 36)
    - Clarke Co., Virginia. (Box 36)
    - Botetourt County, Virginia. Survey and Drawn under the direction of John Wood, 1821. Photocopy. (Box 36)
    - Geological Survey, Monterey Quadrangle, 1941. (Box 36)
    - Geological Survey, Staunton, 1944. (Box 36)
- Photograph Albums
  - Personal Album 1901 (Box-folder 33:1)
    Topics include: Campbell family and home (1901); VMI and Lexington (1901); Col. and Mrs. Robert A. Marr; Willoughby Beach.
  - VMI Cadetship. circa 1901-1904 (Box-folder 33:2)
    Includes drawings, sports photographs.
  - A Book of Memories. 1902-1912 (Box-folder 33:3)
    Topics include: Richmond Hill, NY (1910); Norfolk, VA (1910); Washington, DC (1910, 1912); Willoughby Beach, VA (1910, 1911); Corps at Jamestown Exposition (1907); VMI (1910); International Aviation Meet, Belmont Park, Long Island, NY (Oct. 1910); VMI Football Squad (Nov. 1902); Family pictures; PA RR, NY Tunnel; Bear's Den, VA (1912); Trip through West (1911).
- Printed Material, Misc. (Box 30)